Inventory of the James Barron Papers (1) 1776-1899
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Box 8, 1828-1831., Correspondence of the years 1828-1831 includes several letters from Andrew Jackson and comments in other letters on his election as President. One group of letters exchanged between Barron, Dr. Philip Barraud, and Jackson concern the threat of the dismissal of Barraud from Direc
  - Capt. J. McKeever, to Commodore James Barron, Com'g Navy Yard, Norfolk, Virginia, 11 April [1831]., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:71)
    Re: rumor that Commo. Bainbridge will be restored to the command of the Philadelphia Navy Yard.
  - Letter - Capt. Edm. P. Kennedy, Navy, Washington, to Comdr. James Barron, Navy, Norfolk, Monday, [April 1831]., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:72)
    Re: Barron's move to the command of the Philadelphia Navy Yard and chance of the reinstatement of Commo. Bainbridge at that post.
  - Letter - Capt. Voorhees to Comdr. James Barron, U.S. Naval Station, Gosport, Virginia, 3 May 1831., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:73)
    A description of the U.S. ship John Adams.
  - Letter - Capt. J. McKeever, Baltimore, to Commodore James Barron, Comd'g Navy Yard, Norfolk, Virginia, 5 May [1831]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:74)
    Re: affairs at Washington and General Jackson's good offices.
  - Report - Capt. P.F. Voorhees, U.S. ship John Adams, at sea, off Cape Henry, to Comdr. James Barron, U.S. N. Station, Norfolk, 7 May 1831., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:75)
    Report on the good condition of the ship, as tried under sail.
  - Letter - W.B. Everett, Baltimore, to Commodore James Barron, Norfolk, 7 May 1831., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:76)
    A letter of appreciation.
  - Letter - F. Kirk, Gosport, to Commodore James Barron, 14 May 1831., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:77)
    Regret expressed that Barron is leaving the Gosport Station to take charge of another.
  - Receipt - for household goods in the house of the Commandant of the U.S. Navy Yard, Gosport; from G. Gaer, Navy Store Keeper, to Com. James Barron, 18 May 1831., 1 page. AD. (Box-folder 8:78)
  - Letter - E. Langdon Elwyn, to Commodore [James] Barron, 200 Spruce St., [?], 13 June 1831., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:79)
    Re: orders for his son.
  - Invitation - from the Pennsylvania Society of Cincinnati from Jno. Markland and the Committee, to Comd. James Barron, U.S. Navy, for dinner, 27 June 1831., PADS,C. (Box-folder 8:80)
  - Letter - James Spicer, Philadelphia, to Com. James Barron, Philadelphia, 1 September 1831., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:81)
    Re: "the model of a machine intended for the transportation of the U. States' mail."
  - Letter - Henry Kenyon, Washington, to Commodore James Barron, Philadelphia, September-October 1831., 2 letters. ALsS. (Box-folder 8:82)
    Re: a government appointment; and fresh fish and oysters from the Norfolk area.
  - Draft of an article - marked "The Navy, For the Philadelphia Gazette", signed Barry, 30 November 1831., 8 pages. ADr. (Box-folder 8:83)
    Endorsement on reverse of page 4, "Essays upon Naval Subjects by Commo. Barron."
    A cover note/enclosure: 11 December 1831. J[ames] B[arron], Philadelphia, to Louis McLane. ADr. 1 page.
  - Letter - Will[iam] Knight, Pennsylvania Hosp., to Commodore James Barron, Commanding Yard and Station at Southwark, Philadelphia, December 1831., 2 items. ALS. (Box-folder 8:84)
    Complaining of being held as insane in the hospital. 2 pages.
  Series 9: Box 9
- Box 9, 1832-1834. (Box-folder 9:1-89)
  Papers from the years 1832 to 1834 includes much correspondence with his daughter, Mrs. Mary Barron Blake, Worcester, Massachuetts, and other members of his family; with T. Gatewood, Norfolk, giving news from that area; and with Comm. J.D. Elliott, regarding the republication of material on the Barron-Decatur duel and the trouble that Commodore Elliott had at the Pensacola Naval Station with Captain Dallas. There is correspondence connected with Barron's inventions: the log construction of ships, the steam prow for use on battleships, a valve board pump that was used successfully during the construction of a bridge at Philadelphia, and the air pump for ventilating ships, regarding which there is a report of its successful use off the coast of Brazil and an enquiry from the French Secretary of State for the Navy and Colonies. There is correspondence with Amos Kendall who had invented a steam motor for ships.
  Included also are: an article by Barron for the Philadelphia Gazette on the Navy Bill which was before Congress, written under a pseudonym, 28 January 1832; a statement by Barron on his Revolutionary War Service under his father, Commodore James Barron, the Elder, 7 March 1833; and a copy of an 11 page document from Wm. Duane, Philadelphia, to Joseph Cabell in which he denounces the Nullification Plan as "the South Carolina Sedition," 4 January 1833. There are several drafts of letters sent by Barron during this period.
  - Letter - Dr. William Barton, to Commodore [James] Barron, 24 January 1832., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 9:1)
    Urging Barron to not let it be known that he is willing to leave the Station, because of his enemies there.
  - Invitation - from the Union Insurance Company to Commodore James Barron to Dinner at 3 o'clock in the Mansion House, 4 January 1832., AL. (Box-folder 9:2)
  - Newspaper Article - For the Philadelphia Gazette, signed Amor Patrae, 28 January 1832., 3 pages. AD. (Box-folder 9:3)
    Endorsed: on reverse-side of page 2, "Essays upon Naval Subjects by Como. Barron." Re: the Naval Bill before Congress re: naval grades and the new grade of Admiral.
  - Letters - Capt. Henry Kenyon, Washington, to Commodore James Barron, Philadelphia, January 1832., 2 letters. ALsS. (Box-folder 9:4)
    Re: his difficulties in obtaining a government appointment.
  - Letters - [Comm.] J.D. Elliott, Baltimore,[Maryland] and Carlisle, [Pennsylvania], to Comm. James Barron, Washington and Boston. January-July 1832., 3 letters. ALsS. (Box-folder 9:5)
    Re: publications concerning the Barron-Decatur duel and articles on the subject in the Baltimore Sun.
  - Letter - J[ames] B[arron], Philadelphia, to Amos Kendall, 11 February 1832., 1 page. ADrS. (Box-folder 9:6)
    Re: an article in the Globe regarding John Thompson, a contractor at the Navy Yard.
  - Letter - Amos Kendall, Treasury Department, to Com. James Barron, Navy Yard, Philadelphia, 15 February 1832., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 9:7)
    Re: a claim made by Thompson before the Committee of Claims of the Congress.
  - Letter - Lawrence Penington, Lt. U.S. Navy, Philadelphia, to Com. James Barron, U.S. Navy Yard, Philadelphia, 20 February 1832., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 9:8)
    Regret at being unable to participate in February 22 civic ceremonies.
  - Letter - C.D. Brodie, U.S. Navy Yard, Pensacola, to James Barron, U.S. Navy, Philadelphia, 9 March 1832., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 9:9)
    Mention of Barron's (second) wife; re: difficulties between Comm. Elliott and Capt. Dallas; opposition to Barron in Philadelphia; other naval news.
  - Letter - Capt. E.P. Kennedy, Washington, to Comdr. James Barron, Gosport, 30 March [1832]., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 9:10)
    "The President has dismissed Bryne and all the officers involved in the late duel at Philadelphia."
  - Letter - Levi Woodbury, Navy Department, to Capt. J.D. Elliott, and A. Dallas, 10 April 1832., Cop of ALS. (Box-folder 9:11)
    Exonerating Elliott of charges brought by Dallas. Also, copy sent to Capt. A. Dallas.
  - Letter - Thomas Green, Richmond, to Commodore James Barron, Philadelphia, 14 April 1832., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 9:12)
    Re: payment for land warrants.
  - Letter - [James Barron], Philadelphia, to the Secretary of the Navy, 30 April 1832., 1 page. ADr. (Box-folder 9:13)
    Re: his letterbooks which he is refusing to turn over to the Department.
  - Report - J.D. Elliott, U.S.S. Fairfax, Pensacola Bay, to Commodore James Barron, Commanding Navy Yard, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1 May 1832., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 9:14)
    Marked "Confidential." Report of his difficulties with Capt. Dallas.
  - Request - [James Barron] to the Secretary of the Navy, 9 June 1832., 2 pages. ADr. (Box-folder 9:15)
    Marked "Personal and confidential." Request to be transferred from his command in Philadelphia.
  - Letter - Sir Isaac Coffin, London, to Commodore [James] Barron, 7 July 1832., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 9:16)
    Sent with "Murray's list" and an epitome of his life.
  - Certificate - William Duval's certificate respecting the Revolutionary [War] Services of Commo. James Barron, Senior, 4 August 1832., 3 pages. ADS. (Box-folder 9:17)
  - Letter - Mary Elliott, Carlisle, to Commodore James Barron, Comm. Navy Yard, Philadelphia, 8 August 1832., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 9:18)
    Re: her father who is so ill that he cannot write.
  - Letter - A.M. Green, Sulphur Springs near Fauquier C[our]t Ho[use], Virginia, to Commodore James Barron, Philadelphia, 30 August 1832., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 9:19)
    Re: the Revolutionary War service of Richard Tool.
  - Letter - The Secretary of State for Navy and Colonies, [France], to M. Pinkham, Lieut. U.S. Navy, 3 October 1832., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 9:20)
    Re: the ventilators for ships invented by Barron.
  - Letter - W[illia]m Vinyard, Philadelphia, to Comr. Ja[me]s Barron, Comd'g U.S. Navy Yard, Philadelphia, 12 December 1832., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 9:21)
    Re: repairs needed on the ship "Ruth and Mary."
  - Letter - Tho[mas] G. Broughton, Norfolk, to Commodore James Barron, U.S. Navy, Philadelphia, 12 December 1832., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 9:22)
    Apologies for the non-delivery of the Norfolk Herald.
  - Invitation - Peter A. Browne, Philadelphia, to Commo. James Barron, 16 December 1832., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 9:23)
    Invitation to attend the lectures of the Geological Society of Pennsylvania.
  - Letter - W[illia]m H. Tayloe, Mount Airy, [Pennsylvania], to Comre. [James] Barron, U.S. Navy, Philadelphia, 23 December 1832., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 9:24)
    Re: the Arabian horse Selim (brought to U.S. by Barron after Tripolitan War).
  - W[illia]m Duane, Philadelphia, to Joseph Cabell, 4 January 1833., 11 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 9:25)
    Re: "The South Carolina Sedition" and the dangers of the Nullification.
  - Letter - J.N. Murdaugh, Richmond, Virginia, to Commodore James Barron, U.S. Navy, Philadelphia, 17 January 1833., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 9:26)
    Re: Thomas Boucher, Commodore in Virginia Navy in 1776; the logbook of James Barron, Sr., recently discovered; and the chance that the northern manufacturers will force the "Dissolution of the Union" forming a "Southern Republic."
  - Letters - T. Gatewood, Norfolk, to Commodore James Barron, Philadelphia and Washington, January 1833., 2 letters. ALsS. (Box-folder 9:27)
    Newsy letters of family and naval affairs.
  - Request - Chas. D. Brodie, U.S. Navy Yard, Pensacola, to Commodore James Barron, U.S. Navy, Philadelphia, 2 February 1833., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 9:28)
    Asking his support in conflict with the Naval Department.
  - Complaint - Benjamin King, Navy Yard, Washington City, to Commodore James Barron, Navy Yard, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 12 February 1833., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 9:29)
    Complaint that his pay in the Navy Yard has been reduced to $1.00 per day.
  - Petition - of James Barron, Philadelphia, to Edward Livingston, Secretary of State of the U. States, February 1833., 5 pages. 2 copies. ADr. (Box-folder 9:30)
    Petition for a patent on the log construction of ships.
  - Statement - by Ja[me]s Barron, "the Younger" (Comm. James Barron) regarding his services in the Revolutionary War with his father James Barron, Sr., 7 March 1833., 1 page. ADr. (Box-folder 9:31)
  - Letter - R.J. Cleveland, Havana, to James Barron, U.S. Navy, Philadelphia, 30 March 1833., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 9:32)
    Re: the death by cholera of William Thaler, Consul to Cuba; and his desire to have the post -- asking Barron's recommendation.
  - Letter - President [Andrew] Jackson to Commodore [James] Barron, Washington, 3 May 1833., 1 page. AL, E. (Box-folder 9:33)
    An appointment given for "this evening or early tomorrow morning." Endorsement with list of things which Barron was to discuss with the President.
  - Letter - John Bruce, Washington, to James Barron, Philadelphia, 6 May 1833., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 9:34)
    Plan for building a ship according to Barron's plan on the Ohio River; funds needed.
  - Letter - Geo[rge] S. Blake, Fredericksburg, to Como. James Barron, U.S. Navy, Philadelphia, 16 May 1833., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 9:35)
    Re: the need for Barron's ship of logs, to avoid disasters.
  - Letter - Dr. P[hilip] Barraud, Norfolk, to Commodore [James] Barron, Philadelphia, 10 June 1833., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 9:36)
    Re: a certificate to be signed.
  - Letter - Mary [Barron Blake], Worcester, [Massachusetts], to her father, Com. James Barron, Philadelphia, 1 November 1833., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 9:37)
  - Letter - Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, to Victor Godon, 1 November 1833., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 9:38)
    Re: the grappling hooks used by the ancients in sea battles about which Barron had enquired.
  - Letter - James Biddle to Com. James Barron, 1 November [1833]., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 9:39)
    Re: a ship coming into the Navy Yard to discharge the crew.
  - Letter - John D. Craig, Patent Office, to Com. James Barron, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 12 November 1833., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 9:40)
    Acknowledgments of receipt of specifications for patent of "Prow Ship" or "application of steam power to the purposes of War."
  - Letter - Lieut. Jno. Gwinn, Phila[delphia], to Commo. James Barron, U.S. Navy, 20 November 1833., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 9:41)
    Re: value of the air pump invented by Barron, as used on a cruise off the coast of Brazil.
  - Certificate - The County Commissions of Philadelphia County, Thomas Maguire, John Thompson, David Paul, to Commodore James Barron, U.S. Navy, 26 November 1833., 1 page. ALS. Printed copy included. (Box-folder 9:42)
    Certificate of the value of the valve pump invented by Barron.
  - Report - of the use of pump invented by Barron, 27 November 1833., 1 page. ADr. (Box-folder 9:43)
  - Request - H.S. Crabb, U.S. Navy Yard, Philadelphia, to Comm. James Barron, U.S. Navy, Washington, D.C., 11 December 1833., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 9:44)
    Requesting a recommendation for the position of Purser.
  - Enquiry - Lt. D.D. Baker, Marine Barracks, Philadelphia, to Commodore James Barron, Washington, D.C., 16 December 1833., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 9:45)
    Enquiry regarding the "prospect of a reorganization of the Marine Corps."
  - Request - Otway B. Barraud, Norfolk, to [James Barron], 25 December 1833., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 9:46)
    Request that he sign a certificate "to prosecute Cousin Judy's claim for her father's services."
  - Letter - James Barron, Washington, to Levi Woodbury, Secretary of the Navy, 30 December 1833., 1 page. ADrS. (Box-folder 9:47)
    Re: the steam prow ship that was invented by Barron.
  - Letter - Levi Woodbury, Navy Department, to Com. James Barron, U.S. Navy, Washington, D.C., 31 December 1833., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 9:48)
    Agrees that Barron should seek the consideration of Congress of his steam prow invention.
  - Complaint - H.S. Crabb, U.S. Navy Yard, Philad[elphia], to Comm. James Barron, Washington, D.C., 1 January 1834., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 9:49)
    Complaint of new rates of pay in the Navy Yard.
  - Letter - John Thompson, Jr., Richmond, to Commodore James Barron, Washington City, 2 January 1834., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 9:50)
    Report that warrant has been issued for his Revolutionary War services.
  - Letter - James Barron, Washington, to Andrew Stevenson, Speaker of the House of Representatives, 5 January 1834., 1 page. ADrS. (Box-folder 9:51)
    Asking that his steam prow for battleships be presented to the House for consideration.
  - Letter - Chas. Cassell, Portsmouth, to Commodore James Barron, Washington, D.C., 22 January 1834., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 9:52)
    Asking his support in keeping civilian workers at the Navy Yard.
  - Invitation John Reed, House of Representatives, to Commdre. James Barron, Washington City, 25 January 1834., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 9:53)
    Invitation to explain his steam prow ship to the Committee on Naval Affairs.
  - Letter - Levi Woodbury, Navy Department, to Commo. James Barron, U. States Navy, Washington, D.C., 27 January 1834., Cop of ALS. (Box-folder 9:54)
    Re: "bellows ventilator which have been used in Naval Ships of the U.S. for eight or ten years, with no reward given to Barron, the inventor."
  - Letter - J[ames] B[arron], Washington, to Levi Woodbury, Secretary of the Navy, Washington, 29 January 1834., 1 page. ADrS. (Box-folder 9:55)
    Asking consideration of his bellows ventilator for use on Naval ships.
  - Request - J[ames] B[arron], Washington, to Andrew Stevenson, Speaker of the House of Representatives, 29 January 1834., 1 page. ADrS. (Box-folder 9:56)
    Submitting his invention of ships ventilator for consideration by the Congress.
  - Letters - T. Gatewood, Norfolk, to Commodore James Barron, U.S. Navy, Washington and Philadelphia, January-August 1834., 14 letters. ALsS. (Box-folder 9:57)
    News letters about the family of Barron and Naval events in Norfolk; re: his trouble with a Navy agent, of Dr. Cowdery, of Lt. William Cunningham's Revolutionary War service; re: his son Phil[emon] in the Naval service.
  - Letters - Major J. Gibbons, Richmond, to Commodore James Barron, Navy Yard, Philadelphia and Washington, January-December 1834., 4 letters. ALsS. (Box-folder 9:58)
    Correspondence concerning bounty for Revolutionary War service.
  - Letters - J[ames] B[arron], Washington, to the Secretary of the Navy, 3, 6 February 1834., 2 letters. ADrsS. (Box-folder 9:59)
    Re: filtering machine invented by Barron.
  - Letters - John Rodgers, Navy Commissioners Office, to Levi Woodbury, Secretary of the Navy, 4, 25 February 1834., 2 letters. ALsS. (Box-folder 9:60)
    Re: filtering machine invented by James Barron and submitted to the Navy.
  - Letters - Levi Woodbury, Secretary of the Navy, to Comdre. James Barron, Washington, D.C. 5, 27 February 1834., 2 letters. ALsS. (Box-folder 9:61)
    Re: filtering machine submitted to the Navy.
  - Recommendation - Ed[ward] Byrne, Lt. U.S. Navy, Philadelphia, to Como. Ja[me]s Barron, U.S. Navy, 12 February 1834., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 9:62)
    Recommendation for the ship's ventilator invented by Barron.
  - Letter - H.S. Crabb, U.S. Navy Yard, Philadelphia, to Como. James Barron, U.S. Navy, Washington, 14 February 1834., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 9:63)
    Re: completion of his pump before a committee on inventions.
  - Complaint - Ch. A. Grice, Portsmouth, Virginia, to Commodore James Barron, U.S. Navy, Washington, D.C., 14 February 1834., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 9:64)
    Complaint regarding the rating that the Navy gives to Master Workmen in its yards.
  - Letter - James Barron, Washington, to Levi Woodbury, Secretary of the Navy, Washington, 25 February 1834., ADrS. (Box-folder 9:65)
    Re: a new edition of the book on naval flag signals, the first book having been prepared by Barron. Also second copy of the same.
  - Letters - John D. Craig, Patent Office, to Commodore James Barron, Wash[ington] and Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, February-June 1834., 3 letters. ALsS. (Box-folder 9:66)
    Correspondence regarding patents on a ship ventilator and "cast iron blocks" [for making shells].
  - Letters - Ro. Pollard, Ayletts, King William Co., Virginia, to Commodore James Barron, Philadelphia, 28 March 1834., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 9:67)
    Recollection of meeting Barron at an oyster supper given by Col. Bassett in Williamsburg during the visit of Gen'l Lafayette in 1824; enquiry concerning Byrd Chamberlayne's service in the Revolutionary War.
  - Letters - Amos Kendall, Washington, to Com. Ja[me]s Barron, Philadelphia, March-October 1834., 6 letters. ALsS. (Box-folder 9:68)
    Re: a steam powered ship invented by Kendall about which there is a patent controversy with Dr. Planton (Platon).
  - Letter - James Barron, U.S. Navy Yard, Philad[elphia], to Joel R. Poinsett, Charleston, S.C., 18 April 1834., 1 page. ADrS. (Box-folder 9:69)
    Re: floating dry dock and new type pump invented by Barron.
  - Letter - Capt. E.P. Kennedy, Warrenton, Virginia, to Comdre. James Barron, Navy, Philadelphia, 24 April 1834., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 9:70)
    Re: new Navy regulations and back pay for self and Barron.
  - Letters - J.D. Elliott, Norfolk and Boston, to Como. James Barron, U.S. Navy, Philadelphia and New York, May-July 1834., 4 letters. ALsS. (Box-folder 9:71)
    Re: Barron's actions during the War of 1812 and continuing controversy which concerned Elliott's part in the Barron-Decatur duel.
  - Letters - Thomas Green, Richmond, to Commodore James Barron, Philadelphia, June 1834., 2 letters. ALsS. (Box-folder 9:72)
    Re: Revolutionary War bounties for services of Barron, his father, and Godfrey Ragsdale.
  - Letter - W. Grayson, Washington, to Com. James Barron, Philadelphia, 4 June 1834., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 9:73)
    Re: pump invented by Barron.
  - Request - Mrs. Anne L. Glenn, Norfolk, to Commodore James Barron, Navy, 19 June 1834., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 9:74)
    Requests support for her son who is seeking an appointment to West Point.
  - Letter - W[illia]m Gatewood, Baltimore, to Commodore James Barron, U.S. Navy, Philadelphia, 18 June 1834., 12 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 9:75)
  - Drafts of letters - of [James Barron] to Amos Kendall, June-December 1834., 6 items. ADrs. (Box-folder 9:76)
    Discussions of the "steam cylinder craft" invented by Kendall.
  - Act - "An act for the Relief of Ann Mortimer Barron," signed by A[?] Dinkind, Chief Clerk, Department of State. Endorsed by J[ames] B[arron], 4 September 1834., 1 page. PADrS. (Box-folder 9:77)
    Bill to pay Ann Mortimer Barron, the daughter of William Barron, for services in the Revolutionary War.
  - Letter - H.S. Crabb, Navy Yard, Philadelphia, to Comr. James Barron, Washington, 1 February 1834., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 9:78)
    Re: letters forwarded to Barron.
  - Letter - J[ames] B[arron], Phi[l]a[delphia], to M. Dickinson, 5 July 1834., 1 page. ADrS. (Box-folder 9:79)
    "On the subject of Armed Steam Vessels."
  - Application - James Barron to the Honorable John Forsythe, Secretary of State for the United States, 8 August 1834., 2 pages. ADS. (Box-folder 9:80)
    An application for a patent on the process for making shells of blocks of cast iron.
  - Letter - James Barron, U.S. Navy Yard, Philadelphia, to Robert Armistead, 20 August 1834., 5 pages. Cop of ALS. (Box-folder 9:81)
    "On the [ship] Portia's business," which was sold in Copenhagen because it was impounded there due to the war with Great Britain.
  - Letter - Francis A. Dickens, Washington, to Com. James Barron, 18 September 1834., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 9:82)
    Re: a descendant's war pay claim to be paid by Miss Barron.
  - Letter - Duff Green, Washington, to Commodore [James] Barron, Philadelphia, 24 September 1834., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 9:83)
  - Letter - [Lt.] Philemon Gatewood, Portland, [Maine], to Commodore Ja[me]s Barron, U.S. Navy, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 24 September 1834., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 9:84)
    Description of Maine coastline.
  - [James Barron], Philadel[phia], to Commo. Charles Stewart, 25 September 1834., 1 page. ADr. (Box-folder 9:85)
    Re: "on Prow Ship."
  - Evaluation - Cha[rle]s Stewart, Philade[lphia], to Commodore James Barron, Comm[an]d[in]g the Navy Yard, Philade[lphia], 25 October 1834., pages. ALS, Cop of ALS. (Box-folder 9:86)